to learn their secrets for moving those massive stones. And as it turns out, Cyclops aren't even that strong. They're just really smart about getting material to work for them. Now, the videos you see behind me of large, stone-like, wobbly creatures are the results of this collaboration. OK, so Cyclops might be a mythical creature, but those wonders are still real. People made them. But they also made the myths that surround them, and when it comes to wonders, there's this thick connective tissue between mythology and reality. Take Easter Island, for example. When the Dutch explorers first encountered the island, they asked the people of Rapa Nui how their ancestors could have possibly moved those massive statues. And the Rapa Nui said, "Our ancestors didn't move the statues, because the statues walked themselves." For centuries, this was dismissed, but actually it's true. The statues, known as moai, were transported standing, pivoting from side to side. OK? As spectacular as the moai are for visitors today,
apprenant leurs secrets pour déplacer ces énormes pierres. Il s'avère que les Cyclopes ne sont pas si forts que ça. Ils sont juste très ingénieux avec leurs matériaux. Les créatures pierreuses bancales que vous voyez derrière moi sont le fruit de cette collaboration. OK, les Cyclopes sont des créatures mythiques, mais ces merveilles sont bien réelles. Des gens les ont créées. Mais ils ont aussi créé les mythes qui les entourent. Et quand on parle de merveilles, il y a un épais tissu connectif entre mythologie et réalité. L'Île de Pâques, par exemple. Quand les explorateurs hollandais découvrirent l'île, ils demandèrent aux habitants de Rapa Nui comment leurs ancêtres avaient pu déplacer ces gigantesques statues. Les Rapa Nui ont répondu : « Nos ancêtres n'ont pas déplacé les statues, les statues marchèrent d'elles-mêmes. » Pendant des siècles, cela fut rejeté, mais c'était vrai. Les statues, appelées moais, furent transportées debout, pivotant d'un côté à l'autre. OK ? Les moais sont spectaculaires pour les visiteurs d'aujourd'hui,
you have to imagine being there then, with colossal moai marching around the island. Because the real memorial was not the objects themselves, it was the cultural ritual of bringing a stone to life. So as an architect, I've been chasing that dream. How can we shift our idea of construction to accommodate that mythical side? So what I've been doing is challenging myself with putting on a series of performances of the ancient but pretty straightforward task of just moving and standing big heavy objects, like this 16-foot-tall megalith designed to walk across land and stand vertically;
mais imaginez-vous là-bas à l'époque entourés de moais colossaux marchant sur l'île. Car la vraie valeur n'était pas dans les monuments eux-mêmes mais dans le rituel permettant aux pierres de prendre vie. En tant qu'architecte, je poursuis ce rêve. Comment intégrer ce côté mythique à notre vision de la construction ? Je me suis mis au défi en organisant des représentations sur le thème ancien, mais simple, du déplacement et du redressement d'objets lourds, comme ce mégalithe de cinq mètres conçu pour marcher et se tenir debout ;
or this 4,000-pound behemoth that springs itself to life to dance onstage. And what I've found is that by thinking of architecture not as an end product but as a performance from conception to completion, we end up rediscovering some really smart ways to build things today. You know, so much of the discussion surrounding our future focuses on technology, efficiency and speed. But if I've learned anything from Cyclops, it's that wonders can be smart, spectacular and sustainable -- because of their mass and their mystery.
ou ce géant de deux tonnes qui prend vie pour dancer sur scène. En pensant à l'architecture comme à un spectacle plutôt qu'un produit fini, de la conception à l'aboutissement, on redécouvre des méthodes ingénieuses. Le débat sur notre avenir se concentre sur la technologie, l'efficacité et la rapidité. Mais les Cyclopes m'ont appris une chose : les merveilles sont ingénieuses, spectaculaires et durables... grâce à leur masse et leur mystère.
And while people still want to know how those ancient wonders were built, I've been asking Cyclops how to create the mystery that compels people to ask that very question. Because in an era where we design buildings to last 30, maybe 60 years, I would love to learn how to create something that could entertain for an eternity. Thank you. (Applause)
Pendant que d'autres cherchent encore comment on a construit ces merveilles, j'ai demandé aux Cyclopes comment créer le mystère qui pousse à poser cette question. A l'ère des constructions façonnées pour durer 30, peut-être 60 ans, j'aimerais apprendre comment créer quelque chose qui puisse divertir pour l'éternité. Merci. (Applaudissements)